the infrastructure that we're working on in the traditional capital markets today is 50 years old, right, and it was only invented because that was the most leading technology at the time, but we've really never we thought it until now, and that's what I think is so exciting.
And I think that the regulators, they see that potential, but they also very much worry about precedent right because once you set a new rule that rule is going to be in effect ever more.
Right. And so they want to go a little slower than I think most people are comfortable with because they understand that anything they say really kind of creates this whole new landscape.
And that people need to be able to count on those rules and trust that those rules are going to work.
Here we are with Sandy Cole, the head of innovation at Franklin Templeton. Sandy, it's so great to have you at the defined podcast. Welcome. Thank you so much, Cammy. It's a pleasure to be here.
So I was really looking forward to this conversation because Franklin Templeton has really been at the forefront of this bridge between tradfi and DeFi. You really pioneered your, you know, on chain finance activity.
And I'm really interested to hear about kind of what led you here and how you're looking at the space going forward. But let's start with your background. I'd love to hear, you know, how you came to be interested in this space, and, and help lead this push for DeFi at Franklin Templeton.
Yeah, so I've had kind of a crazy background with all sorts of different experiences. I started off as a reporter and then I became a research analyst in the commodity markets.
And eventually I became super fascinated with how new technologies were changing the opportunities that were available in how finance worked. Right. And so in the late 90s as the Internet was coming out,
I joined one of the dotcom startup consulting firms called Science. And I really helped to pioneer a lot of the new Internet based financial models. So online research, online trading, online banking.
These were all things that we worked on. And people, you know, forget, but it was very revolutionary. Right. The Internet really changed the way that financial markets worked.
And then I began really moving into the consulting side of things and thinking about how traditional financial firms were using emerging technology.
So I first learned about Bitcoin and blockchain probably 2011 2012, but I didn't know what to think of it. Right. I thought it was fascinating technology, but was waiting to kind of see how it all developed. And then in 2016 really started to watch as Ethereum became more and more,
I think, fleshing out the vision of what this space could offer. And when I saw smart contracts and saw the potential in smart contracts, it was like I had that giant aha moment,
because everything in traditional finance, you know, so many of the jobs are really about reconciling what's in all of these off chain, off chain, but paper based documents and reconciling that to the actions that take place in systems
every day. There's like entire teams of people whose entire job it is to just reconcile that every single day. And I was like, wow, if we could start to embed these contracts and automate the terms by which they can execute,
this is going to revolutionize the way that finance works. And that was really when I began to think about and write about what was happening in the space.
I was running a thought leadership practice at Citibank and advising a lot of the big asset managers and hedge funds around the world around how the space was evolving and changing.
And one of the people that I spoke with about this new opportunity set was Jenny Johnson, who's the CEO of Franklin. And Franklin Templeton is a little unusual in that we're really in some ways like a family office. Jenny is the third generation of her family
to be running Franklin Templeton. And so she thinks in a very different way than many CEOs. She really thinks multi generationally and where does she need to push the firm so that we're still successful in 75 more years.
Right. So she was very interested in the blockchain technologies. We began talking. She began the experimentation at Franklin. And I really watched what they were doing. And that was about 2018 that we started doing that.
And by 2021, I was so excited about the work they were doing that I asked Jenny if I could come join the firm. And I came over in 2022 and have been really working to build out and working with our digital asset team to really build out this case set of capabilities
because we truly believe this is the future of finance. That's interesting to hear about the background behind Franklin Templeton and it being more like a family office or having more of those routes that, you know, maybe it, it allows for more out of the box thinking
because it, you know, it's really, it was really exciting to see a traditional asset management company with over a trillion of assets in AUM to be so active on chain. Can you, can you expand on what exactly are the different initiatives and products that you've launched on chain?
Yeah. Well, so one of the areas we were lucky is that Jenny had run operations and technology at Franklin Templeton earlier in her career. So she really understood how we operated in the firm.
And because we have so many mutual funds, we would have hundreds and hundreds of ledgers that we would keep up every day because every mutual fund has both the record of the securities that they're invested into and the record of the shareholders.
And we were doing our own transfer agency work, which was the record of the shareholders. And she had said, Hey, this blockchain is a new type of decentralized ledger.
Let's experiment and see if we can save costs by using a decentralized ledger for our fund administration rather than our traditional way of using mainframe based systems.
And so we decided to launch a tokenized money market fund because money market funds have a daily action in terms of calculating the yield and paying out the yield on the money market fund.
And we thought this is a really good test for us to see if we're going to be able to save money working on blockchain.
And we had to do everything from scratch because it was 2019 and nothing existed. There was no wallets capable of having no your customer and anti money laundering rules.
There was no trading system that could take institutional orders. There was no accounting system that could do fund accounting.
And so we had to build everything ourselves. And that's when we really began to engage with the crypto native companies, because if we're going to operate in the digital asset space, we had to operate with the crypto natives.
And that's how we really began our journey.
So interesting. Okay, so far, what has been the verdict or what's been the takeaway, has this on chain money market fund been more efficient than your traditional mutual fund.
Yeah, so one of our first learnings is that we had tremendous cost savings in operating on blockchain.
But even more importantly, we realized pretty quickly that we could number one go to a far greater number of decimal points in administering our shareholder records, which gave us more accuracy.
And we could begin to because everything settle immediately on chain, we could begin to compile our shareholder record much more quickly and not have to wait till the end of the trading session.
And it opened our mind to this idea that there's a lot of new functionality that has never existed in the traditional financial world that the blockchain was going to be able to enable.
And that's what we have really been able to build in the subsequent years we now have a platform that can do things that no other platform and asset management can do because it's built natively on chain.
Um, I want to double click on kind of the different functionalities that you've discovered, but also on how infrastructure has evolved since 2019 when you first started exploring this you mentioned, you know, lack of.
Okay, we see enabled wallets, and, you know, other infrastructure pieces that you, you saw were missing. How have you seen that the industry has evolved since then. Are you finding it just maybe easier to launch onto in products now because the infrastructure has improved or maybe not maybe you still prefer to do things in house.
So we have seen, first off, tremendous progress in this space. And, you know, we have been able to expand from the original blockchain that we built on, which was the seller network.
And now our Benji infrastructure is actually deployed across nine different public and one private blockchain. So we've been able to really expand and engage with more and more ecosystems, because each of these ecosystems to us is like almost its own digital
nation state, right. It's got its own currency in terms of the native token that you need to pay to purchase the block space. It's got its own entrepreneurs in terms of the developers building applications and projects on the platform.
And so we wanted to be part of many ecosystems because there's so much creativity going on. We wanted people to really think about how they could incorporate the products that we're creating in the functionality and the apps and the protocols that they're developing.
So we've been able to really expand because the ecosystem itself is getting better. We've also been able to patent some of the early technology that we created to be able to operate in the space, which has allowed us to really move quickly.
And we've seen real progress in terms of, you know, they're really starting to be more and more ability to whitelist wallets to be able to have controls in the system to be able to support better abilities to move cross chain.
We've seen improvements in all those areas. So that's given us an ability to leverage more of the tools, the native tools that are being developed in the ecosystem as well.
What are some of those key things that institutions look for when planning to launch a product on chain?
Yeah, so first and foremost is security, right? So we really have a very robust framework that we use to evaluate the blockchains in terms of how decentralized are they, right?
So some blockchains say they're decentralized, but they're not really inviting in sufficient numbers of validators to give us confidence that there is going to be adequate checks and balances in the system.
We look at, you know, what kind of built in safeguards have they put into place to protect against unforeseen bugs to encourage the community to really constantly be testing.
And then we look at the mechanisms for, you know, recording the transactions and how does that actually operate.
And what we've found is that there's different blockchains that work better for different use cases, right? If I'm doing a small order for a more retail focused client, I'm going to want to use one type of chain that has extremely low transaction costs and fast throughput.
But if I'm really executing a huge multi million dollar institutional order, I might want to be willing to pay a little bit more in gas or in other fees to make sure that it's on a blockchain that I feel is going to give longer term security around that record keeping.
So we've kind of developed a whole framework for how we route our orders and how we engage with different blockchains based on the characteristics of the client, and based on the characteristics of the order that they're putting into the system.
That's interesting. So security for sure. Are there any kind of aspects of, yeah, like you mentioned, whitelisting customization that are important and maybe some aspects that you think are lacking or quit or are still, you know, there's room for improvement
for more institutions to come.
Yeah, I mean, I think that, you know, certainly the interoperability is very important. So being able, we work in several different programming languages to be able to cross the different blockchains.
And some of those languages have more built out sets of primitives more built out contract templates than others and, you know, we're watching the development of ecosystems as they start to fill in that toolkit.
And we're able particularly right now with EVM compatible chains, you know, it's easy to spread across all the EVM compatible chains, because the contracts work interoperably.
And so we're, you know, watching the development of that same degree of horizontal expansion, as we look at other ecosystems to see, or, you know, the speed of transaction, if it's not going to be a horizontal system.
And we're through put on the chain so that we can really think about is this a chain we can grow with. So those are the types of characteristics we look for the whitelisting, the way that they handle the allocation of the validators if it's a staking net
or the way that they pay out and determine staking rewards. These are all things that we evaluate as part of our framework.
So there are any blogs inside you have decided not to work with. Well, we have, but I don't want to call out anybody. But basically, there's the standards have to be that, you know, we really are looking for ecosystems that we feel will scale because they're
inviting in a lot of participants. And I'd say that's probably our most important criteria.
Our Genius is a top crypto PR and growth marketing agency, helping brands globally with expert PR and strategic growth marketing. They've worked with 300 plus projects like movement labs and IO.net.
Unlike traditional agencies, they charge only on performance. Their services include earned PR opportunities and marketing services to help boost wallet holders and organic ex followers.
Learn more at www.ThePRGenius.com.
In terms of the functionality that you have seen unlocked because you're working on chain, what are some of these things? And in what ways do you think Franklin Templeton and other firms could, you know, maybe do things on chain that they weren't able to do before?
So, I'm going to point to three specific examples, Kenny, because I think they're just so exciting, right? So the first is today in a traditional money market fund, which is kind of the most basic instrument of the traditional financial ecosystem.
The way that it works is it only trades Monday through Friday. There's a market open. There's a market close. No one can calculate the shareholder record until after the market closes and all the trades are reconciled.
And so I can't figure out who earns the interest from that day's trading until after the markets have closed. And if, let's say, you had owned the money market fund for only a portion of the day, if you're a big corporate treasurer and you move money in, and then you needed to pull that money out before the close, you don't get any interest for that day.
So the three most exciting things we've been able to do with our new platform is we can calculate the shareholder record second by second. So we have an exact shape of the shareholder record.
So if you own the fund for three hours and two minutes, but you don't own it at the close, you still get three hours and two minutes worth of the yield when we are calculating in our system.
The other thing we've been able to do is because we pay out that yield in incremental issuance of new tokens, because the token is the exposure to our fund there it's not just a copy of an off chain record it is the actual exposure.
So we pay out yield in incremental new issuance, and as a result we're able to pay out yield every single calendar day, including Saturdays and Sundays and holidays, and in traditional money market funds they accumulate that yield over the course of an entire month and only pay it out once a month.
So we pay it out every day they most traditional money market funds pay it out once a month. And then the third most exciting thing we're able to do is because the tokens are sitting in wallets, and we know exactly what wallet every token is in, right?
We can allow the token holders to transfer their tokens wallet to wallet or peer to peer. And, you know, if you've ever tried to transfer mutual fund shares it sometimes can take weeks to transfer mutual fund shares.
And there's a ton of offline documentation that you have to fill out and affirmations and, you know, it's a very, very inefficient process which makes those shares not good forms of collateral or not very usable.
Right, but with this peer to peer transfer ability, you know, you can use our money market funds as easily as someone uses Venmo on their phone, right, to actually transfer ownership of the funds and we're finding those three things, right?
So the ability to calculate the shareholder record and understand who earned yield intraday, the ability to pay it through token issuance every single day and the ability to transfer peer to peer is just opening up a lot of new use cases for how to actually
transfer money market funds that just have never existed. So it's very cool. Like, very cool. Yeah, for sure. The third use case is really interesting to me because it really speaks to one of my favorite aspects of DeFi, which is kind of the money levels aspect, the
composability of it. So, and wondering, you know, what's next for a bank key? Are you thinking, you kind of alluded to this, but, you know, holders being able to use those tokens as collateral in DeFi or it, or just more, more broadly, how else are you thinking of using
that? Yeah. So I think that there's going to be entirely new types of financing use cases, right? So a perfect example is in supply chain management, right? If I today am booking, you know, I have cargo that's
driving on a ship into a port, right? That cargo gets checked into the port's electronic booking system. And what happens today is a notification goes out to the owner of that, you know, the buyer of that cargo that the cargo has
and then they begin a process that initiates the payment to the person that shipped the cargo to them. That can take 30 to 60 days, right? What we're looking at already in with smart contracts is the minute that that cargo gets checked into the electronic
system, we're looking at having an Oracle network deliver in that data to the smart contract and immediately releasing the payment and paying for that in our tokenized money market fund by immediately transferring from one wallet to another. So that's collapsing
out at least 30 to 60 days of time in terms of payments moving efficiently. So that's just like one type of new use case that are you actually in conversations with like shipping companies to do that? That's so interesting.
Right. And we're looking at similarly enterprise resource management systems. So all these giant corporations that operate multilaterally and across the globe globally, you know, they have payment systems and employee resource systems that work across, you know, hundreds of different
countries. And it takes tons of cross border payments and they pay all these fees on that. And so we're looking at using our tokenized money market fund as a way of enabling those payments between different internal legal
entities so that they get away from all of these inefficiencies of the banking system. Right. So we're really finding interesting new ways to use these rails to rethink the way that financing works, not just in DeFi, but in more traditional financing as well.
What would the advantage be of using your tokenized money market fund versus say, USCC or a stablecoin? So there's a few examples. There's a few benefits for a tokenized money market fund and a couple shortfalls depending on how you look at it. Right.
From the benefit side. One of the benefits is that there is a regulated set of investments that money market funds can put into their holdings. And they have to report on those holdings every day and put those holdings with a third party custodian.
So you have 100% transparency into the actual underlying holdings of the tokenized money market fund. And those holdings, particularly for a US government money market fund, which is what we offer are very much limited to very high quality assets.
So, because there is this 100% transparency and there is an acknowledgement that the assets being held are very high quality assets, you can post less collateral. If you post it in our tokenized money market fund versus something like USDC.
Right. You'd have to post more USDC to collateralize the same trade. Another benefit is that the yield that we are paying out on this is a full load of the yield that we're able to provide.
If USDC were to pay out the full load of the yield, they would no longer be considered a stablecoin. They'd be considered an investments product, and they'd have to register with the SEC. So we're able to pass through 100% of our yield on the product.
And so there's a couple of the advantages. One of the disadvantages is that this is a know your customer anti money laundering product. So you don't have the same ability to move the fund as freely as you would with USDC wallet to wallet.
Any transfer that takes place with our tokenized money market funds, there has to be identification and underlying know your customer screening that takes place so that we know this is a wallet that is qualified to own the fund.
Okay, that makes sense. Interesting. So, I hadn't thought of the fact that with with Venki because you can pass on all of the yield. Yeah, it's a it's a higher yielding product than, you know, yield bearing stable points.
That's right. Is there any any plans of launching other products. So we're in the midst of launching a whole set of products. Right. So, you know, we are thinking about a lot of people group it under the term real world assets, which I hate that term.
What does that even mean? Like it's basically not in the real world. I guess we all exist in the real world, even the crypto people are in the real world. But we are looking at, you know, we're, as you said, we're a $1.6 trillion asset manager.
So we're looking at tokenizing some of our model portfolios that have equities fixed income alternatives and crypto in the same portfolio. We're looking at tokenizing some of our alternative products themselves.
So we have real estate alternatives, private debt alternatives, private equity alternatives, secondaries. So these are all things that we're looking to tokenize. And we really believe very strongly that it opens up completely new asset classes.
So we call them cultural assets, but there's art, there's collectibles, there's intellectual property. We think these are going to all become new asset classes that every investor holds in their portfolio, because tokenization and blockchain make it very easy now to incorporate those assets into a portfolio.
So what would be the very next product that you launched out of all of them. So we're in the midst right now of launching a couple different versions of our tokenize money market fund in other regions, so that we can have global coverage, right?
So a stablecoin can kind of circulate anywhere in the world, but a registered investment product has to work within that jurisdiction. So we've launched a US version of our money market fund, which is a 40 act.
We've launched a USITS version of our fund out of Luxembourg, which works in many jurisdictions around the world. We have a private version of the fund. And now we just got approved and are finishing up launching a Singaporean BCC structure that works in the Singaporean market.
So we're filling out our product set so that any investor anywhere in the world can have access to our money market funds.
Okay. Well, besides soon performing KYC, do you have to be an accredited investor to buy your money market fund?
No, and that's one of the real beauties of us having tokenized and started with our retail money market fund here in the US. Anybody can buy it. There's an app on your phone.
You can download our Benji app and you can sign up and we finish your KYC AML check quickly and you can immediately start trading. And so you can use it as your own cash management tool and get the full yield that a money market fund offers without needing to go through a broker dealer to get there.
You're able to do that directly with Franklin Templeton so anyone can do.
So you mentioned using these tokens as, you know, in really interesting new use cases as collateral to pay for the supply chain finance.
And in these like business to business use cases. And but how I'm sure you've explored the kind of permission defy aspects there's permissioned lending vault and, you know, KYC evolved.
What do you think of that space? Is it, I know it's like very early, but is that something that you'd explore or what's missing for you to use it?
100%. We're super excited about this space. We're just waiting for the regulators to give us a little more clarity on how they want us to treat a registered product in these pools.
Right, so we're very big believers in liquidity pools. We believe that liquidity pools are going to be a standard part of the future ecosystem.
We're very interested in lending protocols and being able to incorporate our Benji product suite into lending protocols as an option other than stablecoins for that reason that we were talking about before the higher yield, the more stability around the underlying collateral,
the higher transparency and third party custody that they provide. Right. We think that that's going to be a very popular use case. We're working with market makers to begin to be able to make markets against major tokens for our money market fund.
As soon as the regulators give the go ahead, you'll see us really entering from many different facets of the market because we really have such conviction that these are the models that are going to really define the future of finance.
Interesting. Are there specific protocols that you think have their required infrastructure for you to do that?
Yeah, we do, but I can't talk about forward-looking things. So I can't tell you, but yes, there's protocols that we are already in discussions with and we're talking to more every day.
I really feel like this is something as soon as the regulations get clarified, you'll hear a lot of announcements from us on.
Very interesting.
Get 20% APY on ETH with the high growth vault by KELP in one click. High gain uses blue chip DeFi strategies with restaked ETH across ETH, Pendle, usual, and Elixir, managed by strategy pros, ultra yield and upshift to deliver highest rewards on ETH, all in just one click, deposit your ETH, receive high gain ETH, and stay liquid in DeFi.
Trade or use high gain ETH on platforms like Pendle and Balancer, while still stacking rewards. Follow along these steps to get started.
What specific bills are you looking for to get this clarity on how you can participate in liquidity vault?
So I think that there's a couple different things that we're watching. Number one, we're watching some of the stablecoin bills that are coming through. So if you look at the Mika rules in Europe, the markets and crypto assets rules, one of their specific mandates is that you cannot pay yield on a stablecoin.
Right. There's still uncertainty whether the US is going to go in the same direction or not. So that's something that we're watching. We're watching around, you know, how do you treat KYC AML if you're going into a liquidity pool?
Do you need every participant in that pool? Does it have to be basically a permissioned pool? Or is there a way that we can incorporate our tokens into permissionless pools if we can control the KYC AML on our side?
Right. So I think that that's something that we're exploring at this point. And then I think we're always looking at the willingness to accept new forms of digital identity, right? Because there's so many interesting new models around digital identity and how you can attach identity to the transaction.
Right. And so does that provide a whole new pathway where this differential between a permissioned or permissionless pool disappears if you're able to attach identity to the transaction itself? So we're watching all three of those areas very carefully to see how the rules evolved.
And then, of course, we're watching rules around smart contracts and how enforceable are the terms in smart contracts. We're looking at rules around bankruptcy, remoteness, and, you know, if there were to be an issue with a protocol or with a token or with a wallet-based provider.
What are our obligations? Because we are a fiduciary to our clients. So we have legal obligations to our clients. So we're trying to understand what the rules look like in regards to all of that. So there's a bunch of different things we're watching.
We're very engaged. I'm the co-chair of the Commodity Futures Trading Commissions Digital Asset Subcommittee. And we've been working with a big cross product group of both crypto natives and traditional financial players.
I was down. I testified with the SEC Crypto Roundtable, right? So we're trying to be very active and engaged across our firm in helping to shape the regulations because I don't think there's a lot of firms that have been as deep in the space from a traditional
financial perspective as we have. And we're trying to take the regulators on the journey with us.
So we're trying to identify already being a part of potential bills and legislation, about on-chain identity, being a part of potential legislation and having traditional financial firms being open about incorporating those technologies to their operations.
I mean, you've been in this space for so long. What do you think about this shift? I mean, it must be incredible. And how do you think regulators are thinking about this? Are they kind of receptive to it?
Yeah. Well, so I have a very strong point of view on this exact topic because having been in within the system, my whole career, what I see so clearly, Cammy, is that we really need the two sides together, right?
So I don't think that traditional financial firms would have been able to be as innovative and think outside the box and come up with these new models because they have been steeped from their first days of working in a regulatory mindset.
Something outside that regulatory framework was not something they would have ever imagined. So we needed the imagination and the willingness to take a blank sheet of paper and think about what does the technology enable and can it do something completely new.
And that really came from the crypto natives, right? It was that energy, that creativity, that willingness to throw the rulebook out the window that allowed them to really define these models.
But at the same time, a lot of times they keep running up against problems that the traditional financial world has solved many times over for the past hundred or more years.
And so there's a certain depth of knowledge that is also really important if you want these to be long term successful models.
And so it's the coming together of the two that I think has really been the most exciting development, because it's not "tradvi" or "crypto native." It's actually, how does "tradvi" and "crypto native" work together to create something that is more effective?
The way the infrastructure that we're working on in the traditional capital markets today is 50 years old, right? And it was only invented because that was the most leading technology at the time.
But we've really never rethought it until now. And that's what I think is so exciting. And I think that the regulators, they see that potential, but they also very much worry about precedent, right?
Because once you set a new rule, that rule is going to be in effect ever more, right? And so they want to go a little slower than I think most people are comfortable with, because they understand that anything they say really kind of creates this whole new landscape and that people need to be able to count on those rules and trust that those rules are going to work.
But to be very frank with you, we've worked with the regulators steadily at Franklin Templeton since 2019, and we've been able to take them on that journey.
And they have been incredibly receptive to learning with us. And they ask great questions. And sometimes the questions, they ask really help us clarify our own thinking.
So it's really about the partnership and it's bringing the brand new perspective and willingness to throw the rulebook out the window together with the best of what the rules really do give in terms of certainty and protection and figuring out how do you blend them.
So how close do you think you are to getting the regulatory clarity you need to participate and define more fully?
For years and months here in the US, we're going to have a pretty solid sense of what the new rules are going to look like and be able to really operate within them to really expand and extend the use cases and bring more and more assets into the ecosystem.
I mean, don't forget right now, the entire crypto domain is still only about three and a half trillion. And when you look at professionally managed assets, that's over a hundred trillion.
Because broader pools of assets is going to just be a tremendous opportunity for everyone.
So related to that, how do you think the kind of merge of these two worlds? How does that look like so you're talking about bringing a lot of your funds on chain.
But for now, it seems like there's still kind of two separate worlds. You have your off chain mutual funds and you have your on chain.
I don't know, 10 years from now, are they all on chain or do you believe that there will always be kind of, you know, the off chain and on chain world or how do those two worlds work together?
Well, I think that what you will find is probably within the next three to four years, you're going to hit a tipping point where all new fund launches are going to be on chain.
Right, now that doesn't mean that every existing fund is going to migrate on chain because there's actually a lot of work and there's a lot of administration and there's a lot of rule changes and provider changes that would have to happen
to migrate an existing fund on chain. We're seeing this in the ETF space, right? ETFs are so popular now in the US, but it's really only been in the last three or four years that you're seeing active mutual funds move into the ETF wrapper because it's hard.
So I think that you will see new funds, 100% launched online within the next five years. Then I think you will see a migration of today's existing funds, probably starting first with more illiquid funds where the blockchain
provides a lot of operational advantages and with ETFs where already the margins are so thin, being able to find even a few efficiencies through the use of smart contracts and blockchain is going to take cost out of the structure.
So I think at the most liquid and at the most illiquid ends of the spectrum is where you're going to start to see funds migrate, but I think all new fund launches are going to end up being on chain, probably definitely within the next five years.
What about kind of the back office for investment firms because, like you said, that's, you know, like all these kind of manual keeping of ledgers, it seems like that would be an obvious place where, you know, everything should be moving on chain
or why do you think about everything should I 100% agree with you. Unfortunately, a lot of firm systems are 20 years old, 25 years old, 30 years old, and, you know, getting the data out of those systems, getting the processes to engage, even with API is still beyond
many of these systems. So it's going to take, unfortunately, much more time than people expect, because we don't have the ability to bypass the technological limitations of today's financial ecosystem.
It's not a matter of migrating. It's really quite honestly a matter of placing. And so, you know, that's why I think there's going to be this prioritized migration over time. It's probably going to be, I mean, we'll probably still have traditional
mutual funds in 20 years, but instead of being 98% of the market, they may be down to like 5% market, right. Thanks a lot of sense. I mean, similar to what happened with, you know, information and the Internet.
I mean, you still have newspapers, but, you know, they're a small share of what the content that people consume is most most online. That's right. And from the consumer side are like the demand side of these tokens.
And where do you see that coming from? And is that demand there? Or do you still need kind of a new wave of crypto users to come? Because I feel like it's still, you know, pretty, a pretty niche subset of users.
Yes. How do you see that evolve? So here's where I have this whole explanation that I call the account based system versus the wallet based system. Right. And so today, 99% of the way that people invest is through an account based system.
So let's just say you own a new, let's say you own a portfolio that might be three or four different ETFs and maybe a couple mutual funds. And maybe you have some stocks on the side as well. Right.
Every one of those funds and every one of those stocks sit in different accounts. So it's very fragmented. Right. It's very hard to see an aggregated view of all your holdings. There's almost no possibility of inter operating across all of these different accounts.
Right. In a wallet based system, the wallet is a actual holder of all of these assets. And because they're in a tokenized form, they're interoperable. They're composable. Right. So you can really start to use these assets in very new ways.
So what we're watching is adoption of wallet based systems. And there, there's lots of very encouraging signs. Right. If you look at the big neo broker platforms like eToro and Robinhood, they're all moving.
They're all offering wallet based systems, PayPal, wallet based systems. The European Union has just rolled out a European wide system of digital wallets. Right. So as the wallet based ecosystem grows as more and more investors have a wallet.
They're going to want to keep their assets in the wallet because they get so much more utility out of their assets. This is why we're not seeing wide scale redemption of stablecoins back to fiat. People keep their balances in the stablecoins because they don't want to leave the wallet based system.
So I think that it's really growth of the wallet based system that I think will be the enabler of bringing in all of these new products and really allowing the native crypto wallets to grow as well.
And where do you think that wallet based system growth will come from? I think it's coming from these new channels, right? That more and more, I think, younger investors, more and more crypto investors. They're looking for that utility.
You're seeing more credit card companies allowing cryptocurrency based or stablecoin based payments, which is opening up more merchants. And then they have wallets, right? The crypto ETFs that we launched and that other firms launched to have a crypto ETF.
You need to have a wallet to hold the crypto part of the ETF. And so we're putting wallets into traditional financial ecosystems.
And so I think the wallets are beginning to permeate, and that's going to pick up more and more speed, I think.
The goat network is the first sustainable BTC yield chain, powered by decentralized sequencers using multi-coin POS. Goat's mission is to transform BTC and Doge from passive holdings into active yield generating assets through a one-of-a-kind economic model that tokenizes sequencer revenues,
unlocking the full potential of BTC-Fi and meme-fi in a way that's never been done before, and creating new yield opportunities for Bitcoin and Dogecoin holders.
Supply BTC or Doge. Earn BTC in perpetuity.
Get started through our user rewards onboarding portal, onepiece.goat.network.
Especially coupled with what you were saying with more regulatory clarity, now with the stablecoin bill, I mean, banks being able to offer stablecoins directly.
And yeah, maybe people will have less and less of a reason to be in fiat.
That's right.
And maybe we'll get to a point where all of our lives will be in crypto and on chain.
Yeah, I think even for governments that offer fiat, in the US, we may not go to a digital dollar because I think that we have a very advanced commercial banking system.
And so you'll probably see some kinds of forms of commercial bank digital fiat.
But in smaller countries or in countries with less developed financial systems, you'll see central bank digital currencies sit in wallets.
And I think all of this will become interop and reforms of payment. And you're going to be able to use money like instruments like our tokenized money market fund, things like tokenized gold.
These are going to become other forms of payment as well. And so I think that we're moving away from a world where the only forms of payment are fiat currency to a world where fiat currency is just one of many potential forms of payment.
No, it's definitely an exciting time. So, for Franklin Templeton, we talked about kind of the very next things to look for.
So kind of this globalization of Benji, but you also mentioned that you want to bring many other funds on chain.
What are kind of the main candidates to be the next funds that you want? Yeah, so, as I said, within our own ecosystem, we're looking at our traditional products, so our model portfolios and our alternatives.
And then I'd say that we're very, very interested in these cultural assets. And we're looking at things that today are collectible assets or things that are very important, but hard to trade assets like intellectual property.
And I think you'll be hearing about some really exciting new partnerships there from us soon, because we really believe strongly that this is the optimal time to really begin to bring those assets into more and more investor portfolios.
The more diversified your portfolio, the more resilient it's going to be through different economic cycles, the more potential there is to get utility out of your assets, the more potential there is to earn different income streams off different types of assets.
So we're very excited about bringing in new things like art and music and sports and all sorts of new areas that aren't typically thought of as part of a traditional investment portfolio and making them part of our offerings.
I'm just like speculating here I'm wondering who you're you partner with for that is it like a big record label that one you're going to have to read here about a big movie studio or we'll see that's that's really exciting.
In like what timeframe will you be announcing hopefully in the next few months.
Well, we'll definitely watch out for that. Great okay to really touch on the ETFs from which you're obviously very active in you.
You issued a crypto ETFs. What has demand look like is it what you expected, and you know, any kind of insight on demand for like the different cryptocurrencies that you're offering.
Yeah, so it's a very interesting landscape because there's some ETF buyers that are very kind of institutional and I think that the some of the firms that have been very successful in raising assets early had that institutional set of relationships.
And then there's some providers who have very direct to consumer relationships and they too have been very successful early on. Most of our relationships have been with the advisor networks.
So what we have been working on and we launched earlier this year is our model portfolios where we allocate a percent of a portfolio to crypto, just like we allocate to equities or to fixed income or to other alternatives.
So our contemplative has actually taken a very differentiated approach to this in that our model portfolio has a much higher allocation to crypto so we're actually allocating 6% of our portfolio to crypto in our model portfolios.
And we have also taken crypto and incorporated it into the benchmark for the model, which is something that we've not seen our peers do at this point.
So, you know, a lot of times, you know, Bitcoin has been the best performing asset class in, I think, eight of the last 10 years right so just having Bitcoin exposure can make it look like you're outperforming the market.
But if Bitcoin is part of the benchmark for your overall model, then to outperform the market you need to do better than Bitcoin.
And we've incorporated crypto into the benchmark for our model portfolio and what we've used is our multi asset ETF that we call easy peasy.
And that one is every time we launch a new single asset ETF back it's added to our index ETF.
You're getting a more diversified exposure to crypto and so we believe these model portfolios are really going to be the way that we build our assets in crypto ETFs and we think that's part of a value proposition where crypto is part of a well diversified portfolio.
I see. So you are, you're betting more on like a more passive investment approach than kind of like taking which a cryptocurrency or which asset will beat the market but you know just invest in a diversified product.
Yes, our belief is that, you know, when you get to these types of assets, you're always a safer, you're always safer as an investor having diversification.
In case the one you pick to build your exposure and somehow has an issue or isn't the best performing, you know, by diversifying across this is why people don't put all of their money into just one stock right is the whole idea is to diversify
across a whole set of different stock investments and that's our same thinking with crypto.
Again, we think of these as very much nation states and new really kind of investment growth opportunity so you want to hope portfolio of them you don't want to just make your bet on one.
So with the SEC just approving ethan Bitcoin and so many different applications for other cryptos to be included I'm sure you're looking forward to to more cryptos.
All these initiatives in crypto on kind of your long trajectory in this space. What would would success look like for Franklin Templeton in your involvement in crypto.
So for us success will be that this is the way we do business right this isn't something that sits off to the side of our business but it starts to permeate everything we do at Franklin Templeton.
Our head of digital assets he likes to joke that you know he thinks the whole idea of having a digital asset unit is going to be funny in retrospect it's like I belong to the internet department.
Right the internet just became embedded into everything we do and the way that we operate in the world and that's success to us is going to be in digital assets right in crypto is that it just becomes the way we do business.
Right we actually build our future firm on these rails and that's the way we go to market for our clients every single day.
That's so interesting and it really comes back to you know your you started as covering the internet days and back then you talk about.
Companies and now that's become obsolete like every company is a dot com so in the future every company is a crypto company every company is going to be on chain.
Awesome Sandy such an interesting conversation thank you so much for joining me thank you so much for having me it was really fun.